<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pastoral letter written on the occasion of the death of the late Queen of England, of blessed memory with reflections on the greatness of that loss to Europe / by Peter Jurieu ...</title>
            <author>Jurieu, Pierre, 1637-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1206</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36214</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15618869</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15618869</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104185</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46365)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104185)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1151:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pastoral letter written on the occasion of the death of the late Queen of England, of blessed memory with reflections on the greatness of that loss to Europe / by Peter Jurieu ...</title>
                  <author>Jurieu, Pierre, 1637-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>25, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Daniel Brown ... and Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCV [1695]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes half-title page with title: Monsieur Peter Jurieu's pastoral letter on the death of the Queen.</note>
                  <note>Title page printed within mourning border.</note>
                  <note>Includes 3 p. advertisement at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary --  II, --  Queen of England, 1662-1694.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:104185:1"/>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>PETER J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RIE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               </hi>'s PASTORAL LETTER ON THE DEATH of the QUEEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104185:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104185:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PASTORAL LETTER Written on the Occaſion of the DEATH Of the Late <hi>Queen of England</hi> Of Bleſſed Memory. WITH REFLECTIONS ON THE Greatneſs of that Loſs to EUROPE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>PETER J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RIE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>,</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity, and one of the Miniſters of the <hi>French</hi> Church at <hi>Rotterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Daniel Brown,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar:</hi> And <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pastoral_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:104185:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104185:3"/>
            <head>A PASTORAL LETTER ON THE <hi>Death of the Queen.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Dear Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Thoughts are ſo fixt upon the ſad Object of our Grief, that 'tis impoſſible for me to divert them from that, to the Conſideration of thoſe Subjects with which I had deſign'd to entertain the Publick. The Death of the QUEEN <hi>of ENGLAND,</hi> whom God has lately taken away from us, does too entirely poſſeſs every
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104185:4"/>Mind that is touch'd with it, to leave room for any other Reflexions. Out of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Heart, the Mouth muſt ſpeak; Our Loſs is too great, and our Grief too ſtrong to be ſuppreſt. And to whom can I ſpeak of that Loſs more fitly than to you, <hi>my Dear Brethren,</hi> to whom that <hi>Great Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN</hi> was both a Mother and a Protectreſs? But what ſhall I ſay to you on this Occaſion? Shall I attempt to write Her <hi>Funeral Oration?</hi> That is a Deſign far above my ſtrength to execute. It may be ſaid, without flat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ering that <hi>Great Princeſs,</hi> that Her high and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Merit had rais'd Her above all Praiſe. At leaſt 'tis certain, that he that would praiſe Her worthily, muſt be Maſter of all that Elevation of Thought, and Beauty of Expreſſion, which we admire in the beſt Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. But beſides, this is not, in my Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Task that is preſcrib'd to us by our Duty, and the Great Deſign which I have in my view, to inſtruct and ſupport you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Temptations. 'Tis the miſ-fortune of our Time or rather of all former Ages, that 'tis impoſſible, by theſe Elogies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between Truth and Falſhood, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween real and counterfeit Merit, by reaſon of the flattering Colours with which Vice is daub'd over. There is indeed a certain kind of Shame that reſtrains men from running to an Exceſs in the praiſe of Living Perſons, whoſe Actions are for the moſt part daily Refuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their Elogies: But 'tis look'd upon as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104185:4"/>a Duty, and matter of Conſcience, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve no meaſures with reſpect to the Dead. The Heathens did not only Deify their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, for we are inform'd by the Learned, that there were generally three Letters en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grav'd on the Tombs of deceas'd Perſons, which ſignify, <hi>Sacred to the Gods Manes.</hi> When Death has drawn the Curtain, 'tis only the ſhining part of a Life that breaks through, and all the ſhadows, or rather dark parts of it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main hid. Which is the Reaſon that Orators imagine that they are priviledg'd to uſe all manner of liberty on theſe Occaſions: Every thing appears ſtrain'd and exaggerated; they tell us not only all the good Qualities that their Heroes and Heroins had, but alſo alls thoſe that they wanted. And even ſometime, they proceed to ſuch a height of exceſs, as to make Heroical Vertues, of Actions and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents that are real Crimes, not only accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Spirit of the Goſpel, but even ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the dictates of Human Morality. 'Tis plain that Panegyriſts labour more for their own Glory, than for that of their He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes. They would inſpire us with Grief; but the Pains which they take, and the Art which they uſe to compaſs that deſign, ſerve only to convince us that they neither believe, nor are touch'd with what they ſay. True ſorrow is altogether inconſiſtent with ſo much Art; ſo prevailing a Diſorder doth almoſt deter grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Minds from paying juſt Homage to true Worth. For in few years, ſay they, it will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104185:5"/>not be known who is the Flatterer, whether he that Writes the Elogy of a Vicious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or he who Celebrates a Heroin. But I leave this difficulty to be conſider'd by thoſe who ſhall be call'd to immortalize the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory and Vertues of this <hi>Great Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN,</hi> and they will eaſily ſurmount it. For let the Age be as unjuſt, Calumny as ſpiteful, and Flattery as univerſal as 'tis poſſible to conceive them to be; the Brightneſs of that <hi>Princeſs</hi>'s Life, will ſtill be ſufficient to diſſipate all the Clouds, with which a Party that are Enemies to God, would darken it.</p>
            <p>It was the Cuſtom to viſit the Tombs of the Illuſtrious Deceas'd, either to Weep over them, or to cover them with Flowers: But 'tis not barely with ſuch a deſign that we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Tomb of our <hi>Great Queen.</hi> 'Tis true, we cannot behold this great Triumph of Death, without feeling our Souls pierc'd with Grief, and without watering our Boſoms with Tears: But far from coming thither to Weep, we rather come to dry our Tears, and ſeek for Comfort; neither do we bring Flowers, but come to ſeek Fruit. For never did there happen a more inſtructive Accident, or which could better teach us what we are, what we ought to be, and what we ought to think: Theſe are the Leſſons that I intend to lay before you at preſent. But theſe Inſtructions have ſo great a dependance upon the Worth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104185:5"/>and Excellency of the Princeſs whom we Mourn, that I muſt ſay ſomething of Her great Qualities, of the Beauties of Her Body and Mind, and of the Circumſtances of Her Elevation and Fortune.</p>
            <p>MARY <hi>Princeſs of</hi> England had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly all that could render a Perſons lovely, either in reſpect to the Body or to the Mind. The Spirit of Chriſtianity, which deſpiſes Fleſh and Matter, will not ſuffer me to inſiſt upon thoſe viſible Beauties with which that Princeſs was Enrich'd: I ſhall content my ſelf with applying to her what was ſaid of another Queen, whoſe Memory is not yet loſt, that <hi>She was altogether Lovely, and that it was impoſſible not to love her.</hi> But She did not in the leaſt reſemble thoſe Princeſſes who have all that is neceſſary to inſpire Love, but are deſtitute of that Vertue which is neceſſary to preſerve them from Love. 'Tis well known that Beauty is one of the greateſt Temptations to which a Woman is obnoxious: For that is a Temptation which is ever preſent with Her, even when She is fartheſt removed from Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Our QUEEN was from Her Birth of a Sweet and Mild Temper; She was not capable of uttering a hard word; but ſhe was arm'd with ſo powerful and perfect a Modeſty, that never any guilty Thought durſt ariſe in Her preſence. She was naturally Devout, the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104185:6"/>bent of her Heart was toward God; She was full of Compaſſion for the Miſerable, Humble without Meanneſs, Great without Pride, Eaſy of Acceſs, and Affable; and none ever went from her Preſence without being Charmed by Her. With all theſe great Endowments which ſhe ow'd to Her Blood and happy Conſtitution, rather than to Her Education, She fell into the Hands of WILLIAM HENRY <hi>Prince of ORANGE,</hi> while She was yet almoſt a Child. That Prince, at that time in the hotteſt part of his Youth, had acquir'd in the School of Affliction, all the Ripeneſs and Solidity of the Wiſeſt Old Age. He found in the Princeſs a Soul tender and capable of every good Impreſſion. And it may be ſaid, that the Prince never gave a more illuſtrious Proof of his great Ability, than in the manner by which He ſtamp'd His own Image on Her ſoft Mind. He was Her Husband, Her Father, and Her Guide; and in a little time render'd Her one of the beſt Accompliſh'd Perſons in the World. This was His Maſter-piece; He taught Her to Reign long before She was a Queen; He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Her with that Wiſdom, that Silence, that Reſervedneſs, and that Moderation, which is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary to the Family of WILLIAM <hi>of Naſſau, Prince of ORANGE;</hi> who was Sirnam'd, the <hi>Silent,</hi> or the <hi>Reſerv'd.</hi> The Court of this Young Princeſs was diametrically oppoſite to all the other Courts of <hi>Europe:</hi> No gawdy Pleaſures, no Converſations of Vain
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104185:6"/>Wits, no ſcandalous Divertiſements, no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triegues of Gallantry were to be found there. She never would endure any Perſons to be ill ſpoken of in her Preſence, not even the Enemies of the Prince Her Husband: For though She deteſted the Crime, yet She would not ſuffer the Faults of Mankind to be made the matter of common Talk: And as ſoon as any Perſons opened their Mouths on ſuch a deſign, She never fail'd to impoſe Silence, at leaſt by a certain coldneſs, and an Air which chill'd the moſt fiery Tongues. Nor did ſhe take pleaſure in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of publick News, and the Reflections that are uſually made upon them; becauſe ſhe had learned never to diſcover her Sentiments on ſuch Subjects. And therefore thoſe who made Court to Her, never enter'd upon theſe Matters, or at leaſt did not inſiſt upon them: For Courtiers ſtudy the Inclinations of the Prince, to follow them. So that 'twas no wonder that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Converſation before the Princeſs did often ſeem dry: For take away Back-biting and Publick News from ordinary Diſcourſe, and there will be very little left. But to make amends, Her Confidents, who had the honour to ſee Her in private, found in Her an admirable Openneſs of Mind, and a Solidity of Judgment altogether beyond Her Sex: Yet She was ſtill reſerv'd to thoſe whom prudence forbid Her to confide in: Theſe Perfections were accompani'd with a brisk and pleaſant Wit and Humor, which might have ſeem'd inconſiſtent with ſo clear a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104185:7"/>Judgment; for the pleaſant Humor of Ladies proceeds uſually from the Heat of their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, which gets the better of their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But Her Airineſs never carry'd Her to the leaſt Indecency: I believe there is not one Man or Woman in the World that will dare to affirm that they ever heard Her ſpeak a Word that ought not to have been ſpoken, or ſaw Her do an Action that ought not to have been done. This is indeed a high Commendation, but 'tis literally true, and without the leaſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggeration. Her great Soul was never put to a harder Trial, than on the occaſion of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution in <hi>England;</hi> and Her Wiſdom never appear'd with greater luſtre. Never was there a nicer Juncture for a truly Chriſtian Soul, for a Wife that was ſtill a Lover, and a Daught<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er deeply ſenſible of Her Duty. I know ſome perſons to whom She then did the honour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the bottom of Her Soul, which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated by ſo many troubleſome, different, and even contrary Motions; where the Husband and the father were contending together, in that tender Heart, which became the Field of all their Battels. But it may be truly ſaid, that She diſengaged Her ſelf out of all theſe perplexing Circumſtances in an admirable manner: And that She Sacrificed Her Love, Her Quiet, and Her Tenderneſs, to Her Zeal to Her God, to the Publick, and to Her Religion.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104185:7"/>
            <p>Such is the Character of our QUEEN, for the truth of which, and that I have not flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd Her in the Picture that I have made of Her, I may appeal to the King Her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and to the Publick that ador'd Her. 'Tis well known, that Conjugal Love is rare, and uſually very cold among the Great; the Delights of a Court enervate the Soul, and Criminal Paſſions deſtroy Lawful ones, as the flame of Powder and Salt-Peter extinguiſhes the brighteſt Torches. But our pure and chaſt Princes did not diſſipate their Hearts and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections on Foreign Objects. The Court of <hi>England</hi> was become a <hi>Holy Court.</hi> Concubines, Amours, Miſtreſſes, Intrigues and Jealouſies were not heard of there. All the Royal Houſes by the Piety of theſe Great Sovereigns were happily chang'd into Temples and Oratories; where God was ſerv'd ſincerely and purely; where the Divine Service was no longer made a Ceremonial Part of the Royal Grandeur. The Queen had her Hours of Devotion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly regulated. In the Morning, before She went to Her Chappel, She enter'd into Her Cloſet, where She remain'd ſeveral hours. In the Evening She obſerv'd the ſame Method, after She came from thence. How many Prayers did She put up, how many Exerciſes of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and Humiliation has She been ſeen to practice upon Extraordinary Occaſions, ſuch as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104185:8"/>that of the Prince Her Husband's Expedition to <hi>England!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After She came to the Throne, Her Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement made no change in Her Manners, in Her Sweetneſs, and Mildneſs; in Her Piety, Modeſty and Abſtinence from all the Criminal Pleaſures of Worldly Courts. With Her chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Temper, ſhe liv'd more contentedly among Her Women, Her Work, and Her Gardens, than other Princeſſes, do in the midſt of all Their Studi'd Delights, and Pompous Effemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. The Court began to put on a very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Air, from that which it had formerly. Vice, which reigns inſolently every-where elſe, began to hide its face there; a happy preſage that it would quickly diſappear! That Great King, being deeply touch'd with all the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Perfections of His Incomparable QUEEN, after a Poſſeſſion of Seventeen or Eighteen Years, lov'd Her with more Ardour than others do at the birth and heighth of their Paſſion. Beſides a thouſand Proofs that he hath given of His rare Tenderneſs, the QUEEN's Death hath confirm'd it beyond exception. He never ſtirr'd from Her Chamber during the whole courſe of Her Sickneſs. He was often ſeen to burſt forth into Tears; and when She expir'd, Death ſeem'd reſolv'd to put an end to two Lives by one Blow: For the Living KING had as many Signs of Death as the Dying
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104185:8"/>QUEEN. He who never fear'd any thing; whom the greateſt Dangers could never daunt, had not Courage enough to bear ſo Cruel a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. Thoſe numberleſs Deaths which he had often look'd in the face, were never able to ſhock his great Soul. The QUEEN's Death alone found out his tender part, and made him give ground. That lively and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual Grief in a Prince, who is naturally of a dauntleſs and unconcern'd Temper, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of being diſturb'd by Paſſions, is a certain ſign, that the Bonds which united theſe two Souls, were unexpreſſibly ſtrong; And at the ſame time it is a clear Proof of the Heroical Vertue of both. They lov'd each other almoſt to exceſs, becauſe they knew one another to be perfectly vertuous, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be lov'd. For the Love of God, and of his Glory, was the ſource of their Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Love. And upon this Occaſion give me leave to repreſent to you the greatneſs of our Obligation to theſe two Illuſtrious Lovers. They were link'd together by the cloſeſt Ties, they were paſſionately enamour'd of each other; and yet ſuffer'd themſelves to be ſeparated eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Year by a voluntary Exile of Six Months. The King ſacrific'd His deareſt Delights to the Publick Good, and to the Glory of God: And the Loving QUEEN, during theſe tedious Campaigns, ſacrific'd that Dear Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and expos'd Him to the Faithleſneſs of the Sea, to that more terrible treachery of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104185:9"/>Men, and to the Dangers of Battels, in which His Courage engag'd Him every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And all, for the Publick Good, for the Quiet of <hi>Europe,</hi> and for the Glory of Her God.</p>
            <p>Nor was the End of this Princeſs unſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Her Beginning. Young and Fair as She was, a QUEEN, and a Happy QUEEN, ador'd by Her own Subjects, and by Strangers; She welcom'd Death like one that had reaſon to be weary of the World, and as if the World had been weary of Her. Being inform'd on the ſecond day of Her Sickneſs, that Her Diſeaſe was the <hi>Small Pox,</hi> and of a very dangerous Kind, becauſe they did not come out; She addreſt Her ſelf to God in a moſt devout Prayer, and reſign'd Her ſelf to his Hands. When She was advertis'd of the fatal Approaches of Death, She receiv'd the news with a great deal of Firmneſs, and without the leaſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance. She made Her Peace with God, and receiv'd the ſtroke of Death, bowing down Her Head, and lifting up Her Soul towards Heaven, like and Innocent Lamb, or a pure Victim, that offers up it ſelf to its God in a voluntary Oblation.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104185:9"/>
            <p>Think what Advantages the World receiv'd, and might have receiv'd from ſuch a <hi>Queen.</hi> And indeed it may be ſaid that never any Perſon of her Sex, that had a King and a Husband alive, was ſo uſeful to Mankind. Private Perſons may ſpeak of this from their own Experience, What a vaſt multitude of Alms, of Pious and Charitable Works are now with Her before God. She was ſenſibly touch'd with the Affliction of the People of God. She maintain'd every where a great Number of Women of Quality, who had left their Eſtates and Country. She contributed large Sums for the Entertainment of ſo many indigent Perſons, who being driven from their own Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, had without Her aſſiſtance, led a moſt wretched and languiſhing Life. She had the Bleſſings of the Widow and the Orphan; and Her only Grief was that She could not provide for all their Neceſſities.</p>
            <p>Theſe Advantages which we receiv'd, were indeed very precious in the fight of God. But there were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that ſhin'd brighter in the Eyes of Men. Who can enough admire her Wiſdom, Prudence and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in ſharing the burthen of Government with Her Illuſtrious Husband. By Her that Great King could be preſent in ſeveral Places at once. By Her He extended his Empire beyond the Sea. While He commanded Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies on our Frontiers, and ſet bounds to that ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Grandeur, that would have ſwallow'd up all the World: The <hi>Queen</hi> ſupply'd his place on the Throne; She aſſiſted at Her Council four or five hours together, anſwer'd all Propoſals with an admirable Preſence of Mind, and with a piercing clearneſs of Judgment unfolded the moſt knotty difficulties. And in what
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104185:10"/>Time did She rule ſo ſucceſsfully? In the moſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Times that <hi>England</hi> ever ſaw; in the midſt of a thouſand Conſpirators who cover'd their pernicious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns with the ſpecious pretext of a tender Conſcience, and Allegiance to their Sovereign. The Enemies Fleet appear'd on the Coaſts under the formidable Name of an injur'd King, and an incens'd Father: within Cabals were form'd to introduce the Enemy. The King was abſent, buſy'd in defending the Frontiers of His Allies. The <hi>Queen</hi> watches, labours night and day, takes Her meaſures, prevents the Conſpirators, ſees that Fleet diſperſt which came to put Her in Chains, and like a Rock remains unmov'd in the midſt of ſo furious a Tempeſt. Every Campaign renew'd Her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and ſtill She was attended with the ſame glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſucceſs. When the King return'd, She return'd to Her Reſt, She retir'd peaceably to Her Works and Gardens, as if She had been capable of nothing elſe. Juſt like thoſe Heroes of ancient <hi>Rome,</hi> who left their Countrey Labours to command Armies, and having routed the Enemies, and ſecur'd the Commonwealth, return'd again to their little Employments. We have already ſeen what a <hi>Queen</hi> we have loſt: let us now hearken to the Inſtructions that are offer'd to us by the Illuſtrious Deceas'd,</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, She gives us a Leſſon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Vanity of the World, which ought to have a great influence upon us. 'Tis true we ſee daily Examples of it; but they are ſo many, that they cannot make a laſting Impreſſion upon us. We are ſo accuſtom'd to them, that we muſt have remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Examples ſet before us from time to time, to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104185:10"/>rouſe us out of that Stupidity in which we are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. The common People, Citizens, and Tradeſmen periſh before our eyes; but theſe are unpriviledg'd Heads which fall in heaps, and dye unregarded. A thouſand Funerals paſs along our Streets; and are no ſooner paſt than forgotten. They tell us of Princes and Kings that died ſome Ages ago, which now are only ſo many vain Names in Hiſtory. The Preachers draw theſe Goblins out of their Sepulchres, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright us: but they loſe their labour. Death ſeizes on as many Crown'd Heads in this, as in any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Age; for a Crown has no more power now to beſtow Immortality upon him that wears it, than it had a thouſand years ago. But we have always ſome pretext ready to excuſe our want of attention, and to elude the force of ſuch Examples. That Prince was old, and 'twas time for him to be going. This Princeſs was tender, and could not live long. Another had done a great deal of miſchief, and 'twas juſt that he ſhould go to receive the Puniſhments that he deſerv'd. One was hated by his Subjects, and therefore Death was a Bleſſing to him. And another, 'tis true, did little harm, but leſs good, and therefore the World was well rid of him.</p>
            <p>Come, <hi>my dear Brethren and Fellow Mourners,</hi> come and ſee: Behold an Inſtance, that cuts off all ſuch pretexts. Behold a Young Perſon who had receiv'd from Nature all imaginable Favours; ſee a Great Princeſs in the flower of her Age, of a ſound Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, which promiſed a long Life; behold a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Soul, an inexhauſted Source of Good Works, and the Delight of all the World. Behold in this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104185:11"/>Inſtance the Vanity of the World unvail'd, the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the moſt ſhining Creatures, the weakneſs of Humane Confidence, and the diſappointment of all the Hopes of Man. Learn to ralſe your Minds to more ſolid Enjoyments, which Death cannot rob you of. And You, who abuſe your Beauty to ſerve your crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Deſigns, inſtead of making a right uſe of it, as this Great Princeſs did of Hers; come and ſee, in this great Mirrour, what e're long you ſhall likewiſe be.</p>
            <p>Palaces, Guards, well man'd Walls, Ornaments, rich Furniture, delicious Tables, numerous Trains of Servants, and the magnificent Pomp of your guilty Pleaſures; all theſe things ſhall not ſave you from the inſults of Death. <hi>For if thoſe things be done in a green Tree; what ſhall be done in the dry?</hi> Weep, ſaith that <hi>Great Princeſs,</hi> weep for your ſelves, and not for Me. Let us weep for our own Vanity. For She is crown'd with Glory in the Heavens, where She is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Recompence of Her Good Works. But we are left in a World, which rouls like a furious Torrent, where Young and Old are carried headlong to the Abyſs of Death. You Great Perſons, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe your Power, behold this Example; and remember that you ſhall be quickly ſummon'd to receive the Sentence of Death from that Judge, who has lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded our <hi>Queen</hi> with a new and glorious Crown.</p>
            <p>I proceed to a ſecond Leſſon, which is no leſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant than the former. The Queen's Death by diſcovering to us the Vanity of the World, teaches us how to <hi>Live.</hi> And the Piety and Reſignation with which She receiv'd Her Death, inſtructs us how to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104185:11"/>
               <hi>Dye.</hi> After the ſecond Day of Her Sickneſs, they did not conceal from her the Nature of her Diſtemper: and ſhe receiv'd the News with an extraordinary ſtrength of Mind, and with a perfect Submiſſion. Yet there were ſtill ſome hopes left till the ſixth day of Her Diſeaſe. But then the Combination of ſeveral deadly Symptoms, the Small-pox, the Meaſles, <hi>Eriſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelas,</hi> Purple Fever, oppreſſion at Her Breaſt, and loſs of Blood took away all hope of Life. My Lord Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who never left Her, deliver'd the diſmal Meſſage to Her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the whole Court and City were in deſpair, all Perſons were cover'd with Tears, there was nothing to be heard but Sighs and Groans: the King loſt all his Courage, and both He and She were equally bewail'd. The Queen alone receiv'd the fatal Tidings without trouble: She anſwer'd, that She was ready to render to God that Soul which She had receiv'd from him: She addreſs'd her ſelf to him with a moſt ardent Devotion, to obtain his Mercy; She reſign'd Her ſelf to His Will; She begg'd forgiveneſs in the Name, and through the Blood of Her Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt; and recommended to Him, that which was deareſt to Her in the World, the King Her Husband. The reſt of <hi>Wedneſday</hi> and <hi>Thurſday</hi> even to Her Death She paſt in a perfect freedom of Mind, and in the Tranſports and Raptures of a Soul that was wholly devoted to God: She comforted Her Comforter, and edifi'd all Her Aſſiſtants; She receiv'd the Sacrament devoutly, and at laſt yielded up Her Soul to God, without ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering it to be forc'd from Her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Brethren,</hi> the moſt wretched Creatures are not willing to die; they have oftentimes no reaſon to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104185:12"/>deſire to live; yet they will not be perſwaded to a religious Preparation for Death. Let us hearken to this Example, which ſets before us a Queen, Young, Fair, Happy, Lov'd and Ador'd, Ty'd to the World by the firmeſt Bonds: yet all theſe Ties were broken by the hands of Her Piety, as if they had been made of Chaff. <hi>O Death,</hi> ſaid a certain Wiſe man, <hi>how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the remembrance of thee to one that lives peaceably in his own Houſe:</hi> but how much more bitter might it have been to Her who liv'd gloriouſly in a magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Palace? Let us labour then <hi>my Brethren,</hi> to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our ſelves with a holy Confuſion: Let us learn to die in our Meanneſs, in our Baſeneſs, in our Poverty, in our Cottages; as this Young <hi>Queen</hi> hath done in the midſt of all Her Grandeur, and of all Her Glory.</p>
            <p>Theſe are truly great Leſſons, but I have ſound out others that are both higher and more Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I admire the depth of the Providence, and Judgements of God. Who knows, whether we have not occaſion'd the death of our dear <hi>Princeſs,</hi> by our exceſſive Love of Her? If you have ſtudied the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Providence, you ought to have learn'd there, that God takes pleaſure to break our Idols. Of theſe Idols ſome are vain, ſuch as were thoſe of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; and theſe God breaks to pieces in his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in the Fury of his Jealouſie: Others are good and worthy to be lov'd, but they cauſe us to learn too much to the Creature; which is alwayes diſpleaſing to God, and therefore he breaks theſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104185:12"/>in his Mercy, and for our Salvation. Sometimes he produces thoſe Maſter-pieces of his Goodneſs, he ſets them before us, and leaves them with us, ſo long as 'tis neceſſary to make us know them and love them: and then he withdraws his Work and his Image from us, and takes them to himſelf, leaſt we ſhould run to an Exceſs, by loving thoſe Excellent Perſons too much with reſpect to Themſelves, and too little with regard to H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, who is Author of all their Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur and Perfections.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Here we may ſee the Condemnation of the raſh and unwarrantable judgments of ſome who ſay, that God in his Juſtice ſhortens the days of thoſe, who make a bad uſe of them. If ever Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon made a right uſe of her Time, and of her Life, it was certainly our Great and pious <hi>Queen.</hi> But why then did not God prolong Her dayes? Theſe are the depths of God, and the Abyſs of his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom into which we muſt not ſearch. <hi>No man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth either love or hatred, by all that is before them; there is one event to him that ſacrificeth and to him that ſacrificeth not. There is a Juſt Man that periſheth in his Righteouſneſs, and there is a Wicked Man that prolongeth his life in his wickedneſs,</hi> ſaith the Wiſe man. The Wicked deſcends to the Grave with a hoary head; and he whom God loveth is withdrawn from the Evil that is to come. Nor have the Godly any Reaſon to complain of their Lot; they ſhall receive Crowns in Heaven more valuable than thoſe which they may have loſt on Earth. Indeed we who are left here, are wont to complain, but unjuſtly; God takes from us Perſons <hi>of whom the World was not worthy:</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104185:13"/>and why did not we render our ſelves worthy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us learn from hence ſilently to adore the unſearchable Judgments of God. God leaves in the World an infinite number of Perſons, that are like Blemiſhes on a fair Face: <hi>Clouds they are without Water, carried about of Winds. Raging Waves of the Sea, foaming out their own ſhame. Spots in our Feaſts of Charity.</hi> And without reckoning the Wicked, how many uſeleſs Perſons are there in the World? If we conſult our own falſe Wiſdom we may perhaps break forth into ſuch Complaints are theſe: Ah! why are there not a Million of thoſe baſe and guilty Wretches ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crific'd for the Preſervation of One ſo dear and precious a Life? Why do Perſecuters and the Diſturbers of the Publick Quiet prolong their days to be Scourges of Mankind; whilſt the Delights of the World fly away with the ſwiftneſs of a ſhadow, which vaniſhes away, and returns no more? Let us learn, O Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to make a right uſe, or rather to make no uſe at all of that Word which is ſo common amongſt us: <hi>It had been better otherwiſe.</hi> To how many Perſons do we apply this Word; if ſuch a Perſon dies, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, we cry, <hi>It had been better otherwiſe.</hi> Thou knoweſt, O God, and thou makeſt us know that this is a great Error! Whatſoever thou doſt is always beſt. <hi>Thy Will is ever good and perfect.</hi> Grant then that we may acquieſce in it: Inſtruct us in the Depths of thy Wiſdom, and make us ſenſible of the Juſtice of thy Actions; that we may henceforth avoid ſuch prophane Expreſſions.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:104185:13"/>
            <p>In the laſt place, we ought to admire with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the conduct of that God, <hi>who is wonderful in counſel, and excellent in working.</hi> His Providence doth often ſet in order ſecond Cauſes, for the production of Effects, which his eternal Decrees will bring forth in their due time. And this Order appears ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to us, that we cannot believe, that he will change it for another: But on a ſudden we ſee this Order reverſt, and thoſe Chains of ſecond Cauſes broken to pieces. VVe are in an Age of Iron and of Braſs, we live in the Dregs of Time, a Time in which the World and the Church have need of great Agents, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples for the Reformation both of Doctrine and Manners. God ſeem'd to have united the two wiſeſt, moſt pious, and moſt zealous Perſons of our Age, to accompliſh his work, and make a new Chriſtian VVorld. The Union of theſe two great Souls ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to us like the Conjunction of two great Stars, which, we expected, ſhould have ſhed their influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces on both ſides of the Seas, by making Peace to ſpring out of the Earth, and Righteouſneſs to come down from Heaven. And indeed theſe effects were already produc'd in a very ſenſible manner. Alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy God had begun to fulfill our hopes, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his own Deſigns. VVhen, lo <hi>!</hi> by an unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtroke, he had at laſt interrupted the Courſe of thoſe Proſperities, which that Union could not fail to produce.</p>
            <p>By this Conduct God would teach us two things. The Firſt is our own Ignorance: VVe believ'd that he would proceed in one Method, and we ſee that he has taken another. VVhich ought to make us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104185:14"/>our ignorance of the Depths of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. The other thing, that God would teach us, is, that we ſhould alwayes live in an entire, and even in ſome meaſure, in an immediate dependance on his Will. He would not have us to depend too much on humane means. He would give us to underſtand, that his Wiſdom is infinite, and that he has a thouſand ways to arrive at the ſame end. He deprives us of Perſons that ſeem'd to be moſt neceſſary for the execution of his Deſigns; and yet he would not have us doubt of the accompliſhment of them. Let us leave all to him, for if he does not finiſh his VVork by this VVay, he will certainly do it by another. VVe thought that he would have perform'd that great VVork by two excellent Perſons: And he has now taught us that having begun it by Two illuſtrious Heads, he will perfect it by One. Our Great <hi>Queen</hi> has been not a little uſeful to produce thoſe great Events: If ſhe did not lead the Prince to the Throne, ſhe facilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ways to it, which his own VViſdom and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage had open'd. She was the Bond of Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and the Nation: She has eſtabliſh'd that Union during Six years. She has in in her time rais'd our dead Hopes, and reviv'd our dead Church, God reſolves to finiſh without Her, that which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun by Her. And ſo long as God ſhall preſerve to us Him who is the <hi>Breath of our Noſtrils,</hi> according to the Stile of the Prophet, we will breath ſtill, we will hope, and we will live.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant, that the Enemies of the Peace of <hi>Europe</hi> will be ready to conceive great hopes from this mournful Accident. But <hi>He that ſits in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104185:14"/>ſhall laugh</hi> at their devices. He has already ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently explain'd his gracious intentions: And ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable a Providence appear'd evidently in this ſad Juncture; that we may plainly ſee, that he that gave the blow, has no mind to deſtroy us. It was more natural that this Misfortune ſhould have happen'd to us in the Heat of Summer, which is the proper ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for Malignant Diſeaſes: And then the King's ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence might have put an opportunity into the hands of his Enemies to plot miſchief at home. This fatal Death might have alſo ſurpriz'd us, when the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not aſſembl'd; and by this means have given occaſion to the vain hopes, and perhaps alſo to the treaſonable attempts of our Enemies. But the Preſence of the King, the ſitting of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the intire Union that is between Him and them, are ſufficient to diſpel all our Fears, and give us a comfortable aſſurance of the future ſucceſs of the <hi>juſt Cauſe.</hi> God has indeed diſcharg'd the Torrents of his indignation againſt us, but he has ſet bounds to them: He has pour'd forth the Vial of his Fury up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; but he ſtopt it before it came to the bottom. We ought every one of us to <hi>ſtand between the Dead and the Living,</hi> that the Plague may be ſtaid. We ought to beſeech God to inſpite that Great King with wiſe Counſel, that he may continue his aſſiſtance to thoſe to whom his preſence is ſo neceſſary; and to enable him to fill up that great Breach which will be made by his abſence, and by the death of his other Self: And if God ſhall vouchſafe to grant theſe our Petitions, we may ſtill without vanity preſerve our hopes.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:104185:15"/>
            <p>Thus, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> in the midſt of thoſe Tears, which ought never to be dried up, ſince our Loſs can never be repair'd; let us truſt in God, and in the goodneſs of the King, who is of himſelf full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, as you have found by frequent experience. And henceforth we have reaſon to hope, that he will unite in his own Heart all that Charity and Mercy which were formerly divided between Him and the Queen. He that lov'd that amiable and pious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs with ſo much ardour, will certainly cheriſh Her memory, and Her Works will be dear to Him. And ſince Her Goodneſs and Beneficence to you was one of her moſt glorious Works, we may be aſſur'd that our Great Prince will perfect it, rather than over-turn it. All that vaſt number of Altars and living Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, where that Great Queen offer'd up daily Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Charity, are ſo many glorious Monuments, by which the honour of Her Memory is more exalted, than by the moſt Magnificent Tombs. 'Tis true thoſe Altars are but Duſt, and theſe Temples are made of Fleſh and Blood, and muſt e're long be deſtroy'd by Death. But the ſweet odour of theſe Sacrifices ſhall never periſh; it ſhall ſpread it ſelf through the whole Univerſe, it ſhall aſcend to the heavens, and endure throughout all Ages: And we hope that the Royal Bounty of that afflicted Prince, will alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and maintain the Monuments of his dear Queen's Piety, ſo long as our miſeries ſhall require his Aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>As you muſt now unite in the King alone, all thoſe hopes which you formerly divided between Him and the Queen: you ought alſo to joyn for Him alone all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104185:15"/>thoſe ardent Prayers, which you were wont to offer up for Them both, Let us then humbly addreſs our ſelves to God, beſeeching him to cover that Great Prince with his Providence, as with an impenetrable Shield; to preſerve his ſacred Perſon from all the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of his Enemies; to continue and increaſe the Affection and Zeal, which thoſe Nations that God has committed to his charge, have for him; to make him a Terror to all the VVicked, and the Delight of all Good men; to place him for a Sign in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe that piety with which his Soul is already fill'd; to eſtabliſh him in the poſſeſſion of that Grace, which ſhall guide him happily in his Race through this VVorld, and at laſt bring him to Eternal Glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> 15. 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:104185:16"/>
            <head>BOOKS <hi>Printed for</hi> Dan. Browne, <hi>at the</hi> Swan <hi>and</hi> Bible <hi>without</hi> Temple-Bar.</head>
            <p>Rules for Decyphering and explaining all manner of Secret Writing, with exact Methods for Underſtanding Intimations by Signs, Geſtures, or Speech: Alſo an Account of the Secret Ways of Conveying Written Meſſages. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by <hi>Trithemius</hi> Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Welkins,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Cauſe and Cure of Offences, by <hi>R. Kingſton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniſh Decameron,</hi> containing Ten Curious Novells, <hi>viz.</hi> The Rival Ladies, the Miſtakes, the Generous Loves, the Libertine, the Amorous Miſer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the Conqueſt of <hi>Spain</hi> by the <hi>Moors;</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Life of the moſt Illuſtrious Monarch <hi>Almanſor,</hi> and of the ſeveral Revolutions of the mighty Empire of the <hi>Caliphs,</hi> and of the <hi>Affrican</hi> Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>The Vanity of Arts and Sciences, by <hi>Henry Cornielus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Travells of Love and Jealouſie, a Novel.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Serron</hi>'s Novels, <hi>viz.</hi> The Hypocrite: The Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Adultery: The Miſer: Unexpected Choice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:104185:16"/>
            <head>BOOKS <hi>Printed for</hi> Richard Baldwin, <hi>near the</hi> Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-Arms <hi>in</hi> Warwick Lane.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>French</hi> King's Declaration for Settling the General Poll-Tax: Together with his Edict, ordering all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munites both Regular and Secular, and all particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have any <hi>Water</hi> from <hi>Rivers, Brooks, Springs</hi> and <hi>Fountains,</hi> or otherwiſe, (whether for the Ornament of their Houſes, or the Improving of their Eſtates,) to pay ſuch Sums as ſhall be impos'd upon them in Council, in order to have the Benefit of the ſaid <hi>Waters</hi> confirm'd to them for the future. <hi>Given at</hi> Fountain-bleau, <hi>Octob.</hi> 1694. <hi>and Recorded in Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A New and eaſie Method to underſtand the Roman Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: With an exact Chronology of the Reign of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors: And Account of the moſt Eminent Authors, when they flouriſh'd; and an Abridgment of the Roman Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Cuſtoms. By way of Dialogue, for the Uſe of the Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi> Done out of French, with very large Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Amendments, by Mr. <hi>Tho. Brown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miſcellaneous Letters, giving an Account of the Works of the Learned, both at Home and Abroad. To be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed Monthly.</p>
            <p>The Works of <hi>F. Rabelais,</hi> M. D. in five Books; or the Lives, Heroick Deeds, and Saying of the good <hi>Gargantua</hi> and <hi>Pantagruel,</hi> and his Voyage to the Oracle of the Bottle. As alſo his Hiſtorical Letters. To which is added the Author's Life, and Explanatory Remarks. By Mr. <hi>Motteux.</hi> Never before printed in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bibliotheca Politica:</hi> Or an Enquiry into the Ancient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Engliſh Government; with reſpect both to the juſt Extent of Regal Power, and to the Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subject. Wherein all the chief Arguments, as well againſt as for the late Revolution, are impartially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented
<pb facs="tcp:104185:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>and conſidered, In XIII Dialogues. Collected out of the beſt Authors both Ancient and Modern. To which is added, an Alphabetical Index to the whole Work.</p>
            <p>A Collection of Speeches of the Right Honourable <hi>Henry</hi> late Earl of <hi>Warrington,</hi> viz.
<list>
                  <item>I. His Speech upon his being ſworn Mayor of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> in <hi>November</hi> 1691.</item>
                  <item>II. His Speech to the Grand Jury at <hi>Cheſter, April</hi> 13th, 1692.</item>
                  <item>III. His Charge to the Grand Jury at the Quarter Seſſions held for the County of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> on the 11th of <hi>October,</hi> 1692.</item>
                  <item>IV. His Charge to the Grand Jury at the Quarter-Seſſions held for the County of <hi>Cheſter</hi> on the 25th of <hi>April,</hi> 1693.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Letters of State, written by Mr. <hi>John Milton,</hi> to moſt of the Soveraign Princes and Republicks of <hi>Europe,</hi> from the Year 1649. till the Year 1659. To which is added, an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Life. Together with ſeveral of his Poems; and a Catalogue of his Works, never before printed.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to a Paper written by Count <hi>d'Avaux,</hi> the French King's Ambaſſador in <hi>Sweden,</hi> concerning the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals of Peace made by <hi>France</hi> to the Confederates.</p>
            <p>An Eſſay concerning Obedience to the Supream Powers, and the Duty of Subjects in all Revolutions. With ſome Conſiderations touching the preſent Juncture of Affairs.</p>
            <p>An Eſſay concerning the Laws of Nations, and the Rights of Soveraigns. With an Account of what was ſaid at the Council-board by the Civilians upon the Queſtion, whether Their Majeſties Subjects taken a Sea, acting by the late King's Commiſſion, might not be looked on as Pirates? With Reflections upon the Arguments of Sir. <hi>T.P.</hi> and Dr. <hi>Ol.</hi> The Second Edition both by <hi>Matth. Tyndal,</hi> Doctor of Laws.</p>
            <p>The Antiquity and Juſtice of an Oath of Abjuration: In anſwer to a Treatiſe, entituled, The Caſe of an Oath of Abjuration conſidered.</p>
            <p>A Poem on the late Promotions of ſeveral Eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in Church and State. By <hi>N. Tate,</hi> Servant to Their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of the Holy Trinity placed in its Light, by an Anſwer to a late Book, entituled, Animadverſions upon Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Book, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo the Doctrine of the Incarnation of our Lord aſſerted and explained.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
